Hello and welcome back. In this lecture, we will play with our simple MCP server and all the theory we covered in the previous lecture will make sense now.
Let's go through the code step-by-step and line-by-line.
Anthropic, which is the leading company behind MCP, has a Python SDK called MCP.
This library will allow you to start an MCP server in a matter of minutes.
If you have installed the dependencies from requirements.txt while, then you are good to go and you should have the MCP package already installed.
We start by defining a class called Contentful MCP server.
Then we instantiate the fast MCP class which is offered by the MCP package.
We name our MCP server as Contentful MCP server and we declare some variables for Contentful Access Token and Space ID.
We also define the base URL which is used for Contentful API services.
We expect the user to pass the Contentful Access Token and Space ID as environment variable.
If we scroll down a little bit under the Run method, we try to read those from environment variable.
And we check if the token and space ID are set, if not, then we return an error message.
Then finally, we call the Run method which is to start the MCP server and we set the Transport mode to be standard input output.
Remember, we said before when we connect Cloud Disk Top to a local MCP server, then the communication channel is standard input output.
And since this is a local MCP server, we define the Transport to be standard input output.
Now at this point we have the bare minimum code required to start a local MCP server.
Now we need to set up tools that the MCP server will expose to the MCP client.
MCP server tools are basically just a Python function that the MCP client can call to perform specific tasks.
For example, our local MCP server will offer two tools or two methods if you want to call them.
It will offer less Contentful entries and this tool, it will list all the entries in the Contentful space.
And also it will offer Get Contentful entry and this tool will get a specific entry by providing an entry ID.
The MCP client can access and it can also execute these methods or these tools.
If the task requested by the user requires them.
The protocol that makes it happen behind the scenes is called JSON RPC.
JSON RPC is a remote procedure called protocol that MCP has adopted to allow the MCP client to call functions on the MCP server.
Using RPC protocol for the communication between the MCP client and the MCP server is a quite powerful and less complex than building for example REST API.
With RPC you just need a single HTTP endpoint for all the functions that you want to expose and execute.
At the moment I am logged inside my Contentful account.
Our MCP server should be able to list all the entries that you can see under this space.
But also it should be able to get a specific entry by its ID.
So if we pass the entry ID which you can see in the URL our MCP should be able to fetch all the data under that entry.
Now if we go back to the code base I want to call out a few things.
First notice that we use MCP dot tool as a decorator to define that this function is actually an MCP tool.
This decorator come from the fast MCP library and it does all the heavy lifting behind the scenes to expose that this function is a tool that MCP client can call.
My second note we need to define the documentation string under the function and this is very important because the description that we define here it will be used by the AI model to decide which tool from the MCP server to call or execute to fit the user request.
And my last call out notice that this function actually can take a user input as an argument.
In this case in this case the user input is actually the entry ID.
And as you know in security whenever you see a user input you should immediately start thinking of an attack victor.
I don't want to get ahead of myself but whether you are a developer security engineer penetration tester bug bounty whatever.
I want to think of some attack victors that might happen here.
We will touch on this later in the course but it's always good to start thinking what can go wrong from the beginning.
We said before that the MCP server takes care of all the details like passing the authorization token header, great limit error handling and data formatting.
So as you can see under the implementation of each tool we simply make an HTTP request to the Contentful API.
We pass the token and we return the JSON response to the MCP client in case the entry has been retrieved successfully.
Otherwise we just return the error with an error message.
Okay before we finish off this lecture let's quickly recap and try to visualize the data flow from beginning.
When a user asks the model to list all the Contentful entries the AI model will check if there is an MCP server integration that can handle this request then it finds the Contentful MCP server.
Then using the tool documentation string as we said it will decide to call the list Contentful entries tool.
Then using the MCP client it will send an HTTP request to the MCP server.
The payload of this HTTP request it will contain the name of the tool that we want to call as well as any provided user input.
Now when the MCP server receives this request it will execute the list Contentful entries function which makes an API request to Contentful API and then it will retain the response back to the MCP client which will pass the response back to the AI model.
In the next lecture we will integrate this local MCP server with the cloud disk top and you will see this flow in action. Alright guys I hope that this lecture has been informative for you and I would love to see you in the next one.
Thanks for watching.